Guide to the German Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1927-1954 UA.40.09
ULS Archives & Special Collections
German Nationality Room Committee Collection
1927-1954
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. German Nationality Room Committee.
UA.40.09
4 boxes
The German Nationality Room Committee Collection details the planning, funding, and construction of the German Nationality Room in the Cathedral of Learning. The dates of the documents range from 1927 to 1954, and are in both English and German. The collection contains correspondence, finical statements, newspaper clippings, booklets, minutes, programs, a running memo, photographs and other materials related to the German Nationality Room.
Scope and Content Notes
The German Nationality Room Committee Collection contains documents related to the planning, funding and construction of the German Nationality Room in the Cathedral of Learning. The majority of the records range from 1927 to the dedication of the room in 1938, though there is some material from 1939 to 1941. There are also records documenting the dedication of the fairy tale inspired stained glass windows in 1954. The collection includes the committee's minutes, member biographies, financial information, newspaper clippings, publicity materials, correspondence between the committee members, architectural correspondence, programs and booklets, and a running memo related to the German Nationality Room and German Nationality Room Committee. The collection also contains photographs on the design of the room and events it hosted, as well as dedication information on the stained glass windows. The material in this collection includes records in both English and German.
Previous Citation
German Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1927-1954, UA.40.09, University of Pittsburgh Archives
Biography/History
On March 11, 1927, a group of Germans and German-Americans in Pittsburgh appointed a small committee to plan and fundraise for the German Nationality Room in the Cathedral of Learning. For political reasons, the committee did no go abroad for funding or architectural advice, unlike many of the other Nationality Room Committees. The German Room was dedicated on December 2, 1938, to 450 guests. At the time, the design of the room's windows had not been finalized. Fundraising continued, and stained glass windows based on traditional German fairy tales were installed and dedicated on February 7, 1954.
Reinhard Ullrich was the first chairman of the German Nationality Committee, serving as president from 1927 to after the dedication in 1938. The vice chairman of the committee was Henry Meuschke, who helped the committee until his death in 1940. Fritz Ueberle and John Evangelist Loibl were the committee secretaries, and Peter Fischer served as treasurer. The design for the room was drafted by Pittsburgh architect Frank Linder, and the details and construction were carried out under the direction of Gustav Ketterer of Philadephia. The committee also worked with Ruth Crawford Mitchell, the Advisor of the Nationality Rooms for the University of Pittsburgh.
The German Nationality Room is designed in the style of the 16th century German Renaissance, based on the Great Hall of the University of Heidelberg. The entrance bares the crest of the two oldest German Universities (Heidelberg and Leipzig), and the wall panels and window bare the names of famous German poets, musicians, scientists, and philosophers. The ceiling is painted with the crests of different German cities, and the floor is made of oak. The four corners of the room are decorated with characters from German literature. Since 1954, the windows contain stained glass panels that portray characters and events from German fairy tales.
As of 2015, the German Room Committee offers a scholarship for students with a working knowledge of German to study abroad.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred to the University Archives by the Nationality Rooms Program Office in 1999.
German Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Classrooms -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Photographs; Minutes (Administrative records); Financial records; Correspondence; University of Pittsburgh; Clippings (Information artifacts); Nationality Rooms (Cathedral of Learning, Pittsburgh, Pa.); Ullrich, Reinhard; Linder, Frank; Mitchell, Ruth Crawford; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. German Nationality Room Committee.
- Minutes, 1928-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biographies (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Financial Statements, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Publicity Material, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1929-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Running Memo, 1927-1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Design Review (Box 1, Folder 7)
- General Correspondence, 1927-1934 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- General Correspondence, 1935-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Architectural Correspondence, 1927-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Grab Inschriften Im Heidelbergrt Berg Friedhof (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Louis Marhoefer Award (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Presentation Ceremony Program (Box 1, Folder 13)
- University of Pittsburgh Booklets (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Christmas Event Programs, 1942, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Nationality Classrooms Book (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Presentation on German Classroom Windows (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Classroom Design Photographs (Box 2, Folder 18)
- German Classroom Committee Photograph, 1927-1936 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Classroom Photographs, 1938-1954 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Classroom Usage Photographs (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Dedication of German Classroom Photographs, December 2, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Golden Book Photographs, 1939, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Window Presentation Photographs, February 7, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Stained Glass Window Dedication and Thanks, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- The Frog Prince Window Thanks, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Red Riding Hood Window Thanks, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Snow White Window Thanks, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Hansel and Gretel Window Thanks, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- One Eye, Two Eyes, Three Eyes Window Thanks, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Rumpelstilzchen Window Thanks, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Sleeping Beauty Window Thanks, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Snow White and Rose Red Window Thanks, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Cinderella Window Thanks, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Committee Archives Boxes (Box 3, Item 1-5)